<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>itscomputersciencetime</title>
        <link>http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com</link>
        <description></description>
        <generator>Zola</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <atom:link href="http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com/categories/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        
            <item>
                <title>This Blog</title>
                <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com/this-blog/</link>
                <guid>http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com/this-blog/</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog has been a project in itself for me. I was inspired by Chris Done&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;chrisdone.com&#x2F;posts&#x2F;hakyll-and-git-for-you-blog&quot;&gt;blog&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which sets up a nice workflow for a static site.
I wanted to include Haskell in more of my projects, so having a site generated by Haskell was a big incentive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is generated by Hakyll, hosted on Linode by an Apache server, and stored on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;nsmryan&#x2F;itscomputersciencetime.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;github&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server setup was perhaps the most difficult for me, so I took the easy way out and installed one of the pre-made configurations available for linode which installs a LAMP stack.
The only configuration change I made was in &#x2F;etc&#x2F;apache2&#x2F;sites-available&#x2F; where I set the default directory to &#x2F;var&#x2F;www&#x2F;itscomputersciencetime.com.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hakyll part is fairly easy. I created a cabal file (so I can use cabal sandboxes) but the main thing is just building and running the sample Hakyll file. At least initially I have made no changes to the sample site and sample site generating code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hakyll preview command is quite useful for checking out posts before committing them. Once they look the way I want, I commit them to github and then pull them from the linode server. This isn&#x27;t as fancy as Chris Done&#x27;s approach, which was more automated and worth looking at.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on the linode server I build the site into the _sites directory which is a symlink to &#x2F;var&#x2F;www&#x2F;itscomputerscience.com.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process is more complex then I would like. I need to perform multiple steps before adding a post, which will likely turn out to be too much work. I would like to do everything locally and have the site update and build itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats it for now. I&#x27;m glad to be blogging again, and this time with a personalized setup that involves Haskell.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>First Post!</title>
                <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com/first-post/</link>
                <guid>http%3A//itscomputersciencetime.com/first-post/</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The first post on my new blog! My previous blog was &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;itscstime.blogspot.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is currently a combination of hakyll, linode, and github.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
